Silje Synnøve Lyder Hermansen (PhD)

(Postdoctoral fellow, PluriCourts)

Born: 22.09.1981 Telephone: 40 49 91 07

Adress: Sandakerveien 22C Email: s.s.l.hermansen@jus.uio.no

0374 Oslo

Norway Web: siljehermansen.github.io

Publications:

"Delegation of Committee Reports in the European Parliament", with Bjørn Høyland (University of Oslo) and Fang-Yi Chiou (Academie Sinica, Taiwan). European Union Politics. Forthcoming.

2019 *Lær deg R: En innføring i statistikkprogrammets muligheter*. Fagbokforlaget, Oslo, 224 p.

"Striving for influence: The effect of performance on candidate selection". *Party Politics*, 24 (4), pp 382-396

"(Self-)selection and expertise among decision-makers in the European Parliament". The Journal of Legislative Studies, 24 (1), pp 148-172

Invited/special issue:

"Tending the Bar: Strategic Case Allocations in the Court of Justice of the European Union", single-authored. Invited contribution to *Journal of European Public Policy*'s series on EUSA 2019 Best Papers.

Working papers:

"Will Do? Selecting Judges on Preferences and Performance", with Daniel Naurin (PluriCourts)

"Blurred Lines: The Use of Constituency-Based Assistants among Election Seekers", with Andreja Pegan (Northumbria University).

"The sanction that isn't imposed? Roll-call voting loyalty and demotion in European Parliament elections" with Mihail Chiru (UCLouvain) and Thomas Däubler (University of Mannheim)

"How Do Legislated Gender Quotas Impact Representation?", single-authored.

"A different voice in International Courts? Gender and Judicial Behavior in Sexual and Reproductive Rights", with Malcolm Langford, Daniel Naurin and Vegard Vibe

Academic background:

Positions:

05.17 – current **Assistant professor/Post. Doc. PluriCourts** Research area: Independence and accountability as well as University of Oslo judicial behavior in international courts with a special focus on the Court of Justice of the European Union. 08.11 - 01.17**PhD in Political Science** Department of Political Science Title: «Choosing Agents: Members of the European Parliament University of Oslo and their Political Organizations Seen through Report Allocation» Supervisor: Bjørn Høyland The position included 25% teaching obligations. I had two maternity leaves during my contract: One in the winter of 2012/13 and a second in the autumn of 2015. Summer schools 2018 School: "Methods for Computational Social Science" University of Southern California Course: Analyzing and modeling textual data (Los Angeles) 2014 School: "EITM Europe – Empirical implications of theoretical University of Mannheim models". (Mannheim) Course: Theoretical and Methodological Foundations and Accountability and Violence 2013 School: "Parliamentary democracy in Europe" LUISS Guido Carlo School of Course: The European Parliament: Intra- and Inter-Government Institutional Politics and The Rules and Functions of the (Rome) European Parliament 2012 School: ICPSR Summer Program in Quantitative Methods of University of Michigan (Ann Arbor) Course: Introduction to Applied Bayesian Modeling for the Social Sciences, Introduction to Game Theory and Advanced Game Theory 2011 School: Essex Summer School in Social Sciences, University of Universitetet i Essex (Essex) Course: Single Course in Hierarchical Models 02.17-05.17 Writer's grant Fagbokforlaget I have written an introductory book in R (statistics program) for students in social sciences. (publication 2019) 08.13-12.13 Østfold University College **Visiting Lecturer** Teaching introductory course in Research Methods and

Education:

08.07 - 05.10 Master in political science

Statistics.

University of Oslo

Thesis: "Report Allocation in the European Parliament: Selection Criteria of Key-Legislators in EUs Directly Elected Assembly"

In 2008-09, I took a year off to lead the students' magazine Argument.

03.07 - 09.08	Research assistant	University of Oslo
08.06 - 12.06	Single courses in political science	University of Oslo
09.01 - 07.05	Bachelor in political science Consists in two years of law ("DEUG de droit") and an additional year of political science ("Licence de science politique")	Université Panthéon-Sorbonne Paris
09.98 - 07.01	Baccalauréat français I did my high school in France as an exchange student. After three months of intensive language courses, I integrated a regular French class.	Lycée Alain Chartier Bayeux

Invited talks:

University College London (Departmental seminar, 2019)

European Commission (Expert Meeting on the Design of a Multilateral Investment Court, 2018) University of Bergen (Bergen Exchanges on Law & Social Transformation, 2017)

University College Dublin (PADEMIA workshop on Parliamentary accountability: Assessing the link between citizens and elites in national and supranational politics, 2016)

College of Europe (PADEMIA workshop on Recent Developments in the studies of the European Parliament, 2015)

On-campus talks:

Center for European Law (Departmental seminar, 2019)

Comparative Institutions and Regimes Seminar (Department of Political Science, 2018)

PluriCourts (Departmental seminar, 2019, 2017)

PluriCourts (Annual conference, 2018, 2019)

Department of Political Science (Departmental seminar, 2014, 2016)

Conferences:

American Political Science Association (Washington DC, 2014; Boston, 2018)

European Consortium of Political science (ECPR) General Conference (Oslo, 2017; Wrocław 2019) European Political Science Association (Barcelona, 2013; Edinburgh, 2014; Brussels, 2016; Vienna, 2018; Belfast, 2019)

European Union Studies Association (Denver, 2019)

Global and Regional Governance, workshop (Stockholm, 2017)

Joint Sessions (ECPR) (Mons, 2019)

Midwest Political Science Association (Chicago, 2014; 2015)

Norwegian National Conference in Political Science (Trondheim, 2012; Tromsø, 2014; Oslo, 2015, Stavanger 2017, Bergen 2018; Trondheim, 2019)

Service:

Reviewer: European Union Politics, Journal of Common Market Studies, Journal of Legislative

Studies, Scandinavian Political Studies, Journal of European Integration

Organizer: Panel: "Quantitative methods", Norwegian National Conference in Political Science

(Trondheim, 2019)

Departmental seminar: Department of Political Science, University of Oslo (2011-

2012)

Selection Recruitment, training and supervision of research assistant at PluriCourts (2017)

committee: Grants: "Fritt ord" student grants at the Department of Political Science (2014,

2015)

Board Department of Political Science, University of Oslo (2014-2015)

member: Department of Political Science, Université Panthéon-Sorbonne (2004-2005)

Languages:

NorwegianNative speaker.RProficientFrenchProficient.PythonBasicEngelskProficient.LaTeX/MarkdownProficient

Teaching:

Textbook: Lær deg R: En innføring I statistikkprogrammets muligheter (Introductory

book to statistical programming, 2019)

Profession course: Data management in R for practitioners (Course at Unit – Norwegian

Directorate for Information Technologies in Research and Higher Education,

2019)

Course leader: Statistical analysis (masters/PhD level, University of Oslo, 2019)

Research methods and statistics for political scientists (bachelors level,

University College Østfold, 2013)

Lectures: Research methods and statistics for political scientists (masters level,

University of Oslo, 2012, 2013, 2014)

Research methods and statistics in peace and conflict studies (masters level,

University of Oslo, 2015)

Seminar leader: EU decision-making processes and policy areas (bachelors level, University of

Oslo, 2015)

European Union institutions (bachelors level, University of Oslo, 2012)

Political analysis (supervision of bachelors thesis, University of Oslo, 2012) Quantitative methods (masters level, 2011, 2013, 2014, 2019)

Evaluation:

I have also graded in various theses and courses in comparative politics, political analysis and research methods at the bachelors' and masters' level.

Other experiences:

01.11-08.11	Higher Executive Officer	Ministry of Transport and
	Department of Public Roads and Traffic Safety	Communications
	(Section for Traffic Safety and Civil Emergency Planning)	
06.08-06.09	Editor in Chief	argument:
	Argument is an interdisciplinary students' newspaper. I have	
	previously had the position as section editor, member of the	
	editorial team and writer for the same paper.	

1998-2007	Editorial Assistant	Egmont Serieforlaget
	Egmont Serieforlaget - comic books.	

Summer job: My main responsabilities evolved over time from assisting in ongoing projects of archivation to keeping the wheels turning while the editors went on holidays.

Egmont Serieforlaget, 2004-2016 Freelance Parttime translator (French/Norwegian, Norwegian/French, Universitetsforlaget English/Norwegian), proofreader, editor, consultant (reader's Forum for universitetshistorie

KUNSTforum

reports).

02.06-06.06 Royal Norwegian Embassy **Student Intern** in Paris

The internship is intended to give hands-on experience with state administration to students with knowledge of French language and society.